I think it's clear to probably most of
your listeners that the things called
news are mostly propaganda narrative
warfare for some agency and that they
aren't good sources of sense-making
we would hope though that there are some
sources of high signal low noise true
information like maybe scientific
journals like academia so science itself
I hoped this a long time ago ago and I
had the continuous kind of
disappointment you know I started being
like okay Kent I can't trust news to be
true because news is narrative warfare I
can't trust science without actually
really looking at what was the
methodology employed how was it funded
what were the axioms that the team was
using what were the logical transforms
am i seeing all of their data or was a
cherry pick data and as we as I started
to kind unfold to say where are the high
signal low noise sources that I can
offload some of the cognitive complexity
of making sense of the world to the
answer is really sad right I don't know
any sources that are very high signal
and low noise or across lots of areas so
they don't start being like well why is
that
and what would it take to fix that what
would it take to make a world ahead an
intact information ecology well that
requires understanding why the current
information ecology is as broken as it
is and we're starting to touch on a
couple things here but this goes deep
and how do we make good choices if we
don't have good sense making well
obviously we can't but due to increasing
technological capacity right increasing
population multiplied by increasing
impact per person we're making more and
more consequential choices with worse
and worse sense mate
to inform those choices which is kind of
running increasingly fast through the
woods increasingly blind right and so I
think many of the people that you've had
on Robo wisdom have been in a deep
inquiry around how do we actually fix
our own sense making and it's some of
what has brought us to have
conversations with each other because a
part of how we work with our own sense
making as we recognize the cognitive
complexity of issues that the world
faces is more than a single person can
process a single brain that can't
actually hold that cognitive complexity
so it requires collective intelligence
and collective sense making
but I can't just offload the cognitive
complexity to some Authority because I
can't trust that they're actually doing
good sense making maybe they're doing
good sense making within a very limited
context but then the application of that
outside of the context is different and
maybe there's even distortions within
their context so I have to try and find
other people that are also really
endeavoring to sense make well which
means they have to understand what
causes failures and sense making and
then we have to see can we create
relationships with each other that
removed the distortion basis that is
normally there so I think I think what I
from what I have seen of rebel wisdom
this is probably the strange attractor
of what is bringing everybody to watch
it is people who are trying to make
sense of the world better themselves and
are trying to find sources of content of
other other people that have been trying
to make sense of it well which is what
I'm excited about and so those are just
some opening thoughts and yeah I look
forward to getting into why we have as
broken and information ecology as we
have and what it would take to correct
that at a at scale and how we can make
sense of the world even in the broken
information ecology now in terms of
practical process
I've never actually shared publicly
these types of frameworks before so this
feels fun and exciting and I hope that's
useful as I've been trying to make sense
of the world making sense of why since
making it so hard is pretty central
there's a famous quote I think
attributed to Einstein make things as
simple as possible but not simpler as
simple as possible really the goal isn't
is as clear as possible right but
simpler would mean it's wrong like it's
not accurate anymore if I'm you know
you're gonna have to face this doing
media work there will be pressures on
you to say hey people can't pay
attention more than sound bytes you got
to make it five minute chunks so the
word size is too big make it for an
eighth grade level right which is saying
people are dumb
so spoon feed them stuff that dumb
people can handle which to the degree
you do that and it's successful will
keep people dumb but that's what that's
what like those are the pressures in in
anyone doing broadcast even for a
hopefully good intention right and if we
want people to actually be able to make
sense of the world well you can't do it
in very short periods of time with lots
of distraction and oversimplified like
if you if you look at anyone who
actually increased the sense making
capacity of the world you look at any
scientist or philosopher they didn't do
it in tweets and they didn't do it
radically distracted and they didn't do
it in a dumb down process right like I
have I have so many people who have
written to me saying like we want to
create a new kind of Education
young people we want to create a new
kind of education that makes everybody
like Bucky fuller or Leonardo sits
conditions polymaths and they say this
because I've written some stuff on that
topic and that they have some sense that
they could lead that and I'm like
have you read Bucky's books like well no
we mostly don't read books and have you
read the references in Bucky's books
just see the amount of shit that he read
and referenced to make sense of things
well and so there's a there there's a
decoupling of the sense of the agency
possible with what it takes to do it
it's you know like that there's a saying
everywhere in almost all domains to this
effect of like everybody wants to be
buff but nobody wants to lift heavy ass
weights or everybody wants to win and
nobody wants to work harder there's
something like that that happens here is
if I want to be able to make sense of
the world well I have to work at that
and if I want to be able to make sense
of the world better that the world
better than I currently do like
attention requires being trained just
like muscles require being trained
thinking clearly requires being trained
and anytime there's a hormetic process
you know hormesis is the principle by
which you stress an adaptive system to
increase its adaptive capacity so I have
to stress a muscle to get the muscle to
grow if I'm lifting an amount of weight
that's super easy the muscle there's no
input that says the muscle needs to be
bigger and there's a cost to getting
bigger right so it's only gonna go
through that cost if it's being stressed
and the same is true like if I expose
myself to more heat and more cold than
as comfortable actually gain greater
metabolic flexibility to deal with heat
and cold which means that if I stay in
an environment where I always have
heating and air conditioning I'll
actually lose metabolic flexibility you
have to stress the system to be able to
grow the system and in a particular kind
of way and not all stressors are gonna
grow the system but this is definitely
true cognitively which means if I keep
paying attention to hyper normal stimuli
that are
moving quickly so I get the stimuli of
lots of novelty I'm gonna be decreasing
my attention but if I want to have any
kind of nuanced view I have to be able
to hold multiple partial views in
working memory it's not that some people
have good memory or good attention and
other people don't intrinsically it any
more than some people are buff and some
aren't intrinsically it's developable
but it has to actually be developed so
so the impulse to say hey make it really
simple so everybody can get it and the
impulse to say help people actually make
sense of the world well or are different
things now some people will make stuff
technical seeming intentionally to
obscure it as a power game right so that
to encourage others to defer their sense
making to them I understand this complex
shit you're not gonna be able to
understand this or defer Authority to me
we will we want to do something if we
actually want to empower people I don't
want them to defer their sense-making to
me but I also don't want them to do lazy
shitty sense-making or defer it to
anyone else which means I want them to
grow the quality of their own sense
making which means to grow the depth of
their care right anti nihilism to grow
the depth of their care to grow the
depth of their earnestness their own
self-reflexiveness to pay attention to
their biases and where their sloppiness
and thinking their own skills and
capacity want them to grow their
attention span and both the clarity of
their logic and the clarity of their
intuition and the noticing when
something's coming from intuition or
logic and how to relate those like all
of those things but that's actually what
increasing sovereignty means so
information apology is that there's a
there's a whole ecosystem of information
right like we have information coming in
from marketing information coming in
from government sources from campaigning
from just what our neighbors tell us and
our friends tell us from social media
from like and we use information to make
sense of the world to make choices that
are aligned with whatever our goals are
and our values and what's meaningful to
us
and what we hope is that the information
around us is mostly true and
representative of reality so that we can
use that to make choices that will be
effective when I say broken information
ecology it means that we can't trust
that most of the information coming in
is true and representative of reality
and will inform good choice making and
so then this is where we have to get
into ok so where does information come
from right signals are being shared by
people and by groups of people that have
shared agency like corporations and
governments and political parties and
religions and whatever right and so we
want to start getting into why do people
share information other than just
sharing what is true and representative
of reality this is actually a really key
thing to start to understand so maybe
I'll actually define something that I
was just referencing which is the
difference between true and truthful
it's a first important distinction when
we say someone's being truthful what we
mean is that what they if you're being
truthful with me it means that what you
are sharing maps to what you believe
right that there's a correspondence
between the signal that you're
communicating to me and what you believe
is true so we can look at breakdowns of
truthfulness which is where people are
distorting information with some
intentionality and that can either be
through overt lying or through lying
through omission or lying through
emphasis bias right those kinds of
things so that's truthful and when we
say something is true what we typically
mean and this is actually this gets very
nuanced and we end up having to get into
like fundamental epistemology ontology
concepts of what does it mean for
something to be true what are our
fundamental axioms about the nature of
reality I'll put that on hold for now
and just say in general if we say that
someone's saying something that's true
we don't just mean that there's a
correspondence between what they're
saying and what they think but there's a
corresponds between what they're saying
and some independently verifiable
reality and so of course someone can be
truthful meaning they say what they
believe but what they believe is
misinformed because they did
sense-making poorly so they're
propagating information honestly but
that is not true and so we need to look
at distortions in both of these there's
a third thing which is representative
which is it's possible for someone to be
truthful share exactly what they think
is going on and that what they're
sharing is actually true they've
actually done good epistemology and
empirically validated that what they're
saying maps to reality and in some clear
way and yet the interpretation I get
from that will still actually mislead me
because it's not the true information is
not representative of the entire context
well articles published and famous
journals peer-reviewed scientific
journals like Journal of American
Medical Association five years later
we'll see that a major percentage of
them something like fifty percent are
found to be mostly inaccurate fifty
percent is a coin toss right or we see
the replication crisis or we see that
the things that get studied even if it's
true information it can be misleading
because for the most part where does the
money to fund the research come from
it's gonna come within capitalism mostly
where there's some ROI on the research
and so some areas have moral ROI than
others so even a bunch of true
information but that is weighted towards
certain parts of the information ecology
over others create misrepresentation
through preponderance of information
right so even a bunch of true
information can create distortion so
then you start to say oh okay so the
essence of science within the philosophy
of science the essence of it is
earnestness of inquiry right it's
empiricism but then earnestness of
inquiry eddington defined science as the
earnest endeavor to put into order the
facts of experience and the essence of
capitalism is see you can say the
essence of science is no bias
right at least the idea the spirit of it
we can get into where even the
philosophy of science has built an
axiomatic bias later but then the in
capitalism it is about optimizing for
bias right like I actually have an
agency that I'm trying to get ahead I
have intention to increase my balance
sheet and so if there is capital funding
of science it's going to fund the things
that create ROI on that research so we
can keep doing more research that
creates both a reason to distort the
info and the reason to withhold
information that is a source of
competitive advantage a reason to create
this info to other competitors and to at
least wait you know of course in biotech
if I can get a patent on a synthetic
molecule and I can't get a patent on a
natural molecule does a lot more money
is gonna go into synthetic molecules in
natural and then we look it and say well
there's not that many phase 3 clinical
trials on herbs and there are on Pharma
meds so the pharma meds must be more
accurate no this is a even true
information preponderance of data is
going to create problems right and
that's actually true information that is
being shared truthfully that would still
be misrepresentative of
reality so this is where I have to say
do I have some sense of what the actual
territory is and do I have a sense that
the map that's being created actually
maps onto the territory reasonably well
because sense making means map
generation right to be able to make
choices of how we navigate how we do
choice making in relationships with some
actual territory so that's true truthful
and then representative and we can look
at distortions and all three of those so
when we look at white as an individual
distort information the the most
fundamental way of thinking about it is
there's this idea in terms of signaling
like if I'm just nature watching and I'm
watching what is happening with rabbits
and trees and birds I'm getting
information about them that they aren't
even intending
to transmit and so the information is
just reflective right lights actually
reflecting off of them of the nature of
reality as soon as there's an agent that
can share information strategically for
an intention then I don't know if what
they're sharing is reflective of reality
or reflective of what they think will
advance their intention and that's kind
of the key distinction is that the
moment we get abstract signaling which
language allows us and the ability to
kind of forecast in our ability to model
each other and your well-being and the
basis of your agency doesn't seem
coupled with my well-being in the basis
of my agency perfectly in the case of
the partner wanting to cheat and get
away with it right there's a decoupling
of well being an agency in the case of
if I'm a marketer of a product and I
want you to purchase it
whether my product is actually the best
product or not whether a competitor's
product is better whether you need the
product or not I want you to think that
you need it and to think that mine is
the best right so there's a breakdown
between what seems to be in my
well-being and what seems to be in your
well-being so wherever there is a any
misalignment in agency and there's the
ability to share signal for strategic
purposes then you have a basis to have
signal that's being shared that isn't
just truthful right so then we look at
where is that happening and it's fucking
everywhere right to really gross or
subtle degrees pretty much everywhere
and sometimes for dreadful purposes like
I mean you got the prosaic purposes
which are basically market type dynamics
which most of the dynamics in the world
or market dynamics or at least
influenced by market dynamics right
market dynamics are fundamentally at
least partially if not mostly rivalries
meaning my balance she can get ahead
independent of your balance she getting
ahead and definitely independent of the
Commons right and so in a market type
dynamic I'm going to be sharing
information and this is why buyer beware
but as soon buyer beware is not just you
know check to make sure that the car
isn't about to break down it's also
check to make sure that the information
shared is being true because if I'm
actually sharing information as a
service right and you're purchasing that
information whether it's whether you're
paying for it with your attention that's
being monetized through an ad or you're
paying for it directly or whatever
there's nothing that says I'm sharing
true and truthful information so in
market type dynamics the the goal of
marketing is that there is si as a
company and from the supply side of
supply and demand dynamics the goal is
to compel the purchasers action in a
particular way which means as a company
I want to do sense making for you
because I want to control your choice
making I at least want to influence your
choice making I'm not actually
interested in your sovereignty and I'm
not even that interested in your quality
of life I'm interested in you thinking
that I'm interested in your quality of
life I'm interested in you believing
that my stuff will affect your quality
of life but whether that actually
corresponds or not I don't care in fact
if I can sell you food that is very
addictive or cigarettes or social media
or media or porn or whatever it is that
actually decreases your baseline
happiness but then makes you need
another hit faster and it's addictive
that's really good for lifetime revenue
of a customer and to the degree that my
fiduciary responsibility is to maximize
profitability for me and my shareholders
and so I need to maximize lifetime
revenue of my customers multiplied by
maximizing the customer base addiction
is the most profitable thing I can get
right where that's never in the best
interest of the customer now as a
corporation where I get to employ a
whole bunch of people to do market
research into split-test
ads and to see what works best and to
use psychological insights and to be
thinking about your choice making more
than you're thinking about your choice
making not only is the information I'm
sharing with you not just truthful and
it's a form of kind of narrative warfare
because that we're agents that are
actually competing for what you do are
you I want you to do something in
particular you want to do it
for you those aren't the same thing but
it's actually an asymmetric warfare
because I have a lot more ongoing team
and focus now especially as you start to
look at a big corporation empowered by
AI and Big Data and etc it's radically
asymmetric info warfare that you don't
even know it's happening
right you don't even know you're engaged
in so we can see that and but all the
way down to the little guy in in a
market right who's just peddling where's
his incentive is to compel people to buy
the thing not to really adequately
inform them that he just marked the
price up a lot from where he got it down
the way and if they go down the way off
the beaten path like the other stuff is
better and so this is Rubik wa tiss
right okay and then as we're exploring
reasons that people share things that
are not fully truthful and and
representative there of course things
worse than this
this is I would say most of where the
distortion comes from is agency
misalignment well it's always agency
misalignment right mostly we'll call
that market but any sources where you
have some agent whether it's a come a
company or a country or a person that
can think about their own well-being
independent of the well-being of other
agents and/or the Commons then there is
a basis for them to optimize their
well-being at with some externality in
the same way we externalize cost to the
environment we X connects turn Eliza
cost to the information environment in
externalize cost to the information
environment is like disinformation is
pollution to the information ecology
right that's a kind of a good way of
thinking about it and as ubiquity Bic
witness as pollution is where we see
that the snow on the top of Mount
Everest is full of pollution right of
many different kinds I would say
information ecology pollution is more
Rubik witness because it's not just big
industrial players doing it it's
everybody doing it and you can't even
see it as clearly
but even people will create distortions
and information for seemingly positive
reasons like first there's kind of
innocuous reasons like okay I'm gonna
write a testimonial or an endorsement
for my friend's book because they're my
friend even though I think there's stuff
wrong in their book it wouldn't be that
gracious of me to say that and maybe
there's some game theoretic stuff in
there like they wrote a nice testimonial
for my book and I want them to keep
doing that and so my giving the
endorsement of my whatever credibility
that other people proxy their sense
making to me I'm now you know proxying
that credibility over here is not
necessarily true even if it's not that
they did the endorsement on my book and
I just am supportive of them taking a
positive step that doesn't necessarily
mean that anyone else who sees that I
offered that testimonial and is using
that as a method of their own sense
making knows why I did it so here's the
other thing as a decoupling of the
signal that I'm sharing with the
intention that I'm sharing it for and so
I might be sharing something with you
and I have four or five complex
intentions I might not share any of them
with you or maybe I shared one when
you're getting information from a news
channel and you're like oh this news
channel wants to maximize my time on
site and it can do that through
appealing to my cognitive biases and my
emotional biases and my identity biases
it can do that through things that are
inflammatory it can do that through all
kinds of things that are hyper normal
stimulus and that hijack my attention
this is where it's competing for my
attention against where I would want to
put my attention because it's monetizing
my attention right so I have to factor
the agency the intention of the news
station and try and remove that artifact
from the information to try and infer
what the true information might be
basically to infer what the source of
distortion might be the same of the
political candidate the same with
science that's coming forward and I'm
looking at
okay so who's who is seeking more grant
funding and what is easiest to fund and
where are their standard model biases
where only the things people are only
going to share the shit that's gonna get
them more funding and that's gonna get
tenure where they have to defend the
thing that got them the Nobel Prize if
they're not may not be true anymore for
ego and identity biases got a factor all
of those kinds of sources of possible
bias and so this is the first I would
say kind of valuable thing when you're
trying to do sense making is to
recognize that the signal that you're
getting everywhere is mostly strategic
um strategic on the part of which is
just another way to say intentional on
the part of the agent sharing it for
their purposes not yours and where there
is a dis alignment between your well
being and theirs or at least an apparent
one then what their basis for intention
might actually suck for you and even if
there seems to be alignment you still
don't want lied to for your good you
still want your information so I would
say one of the first things we want to
do when we start to do sense making is
to look at why is anyone sharing what
they're sharing and not assuming that
they are being truthful
[Music]
so basically truthful is about game
theory right truthful is about the fact
that people are lying all the time
and
okay we're actually gonna say a little
bit more about that one formula when
you're playing poker you learn how to
bluff
because it it's not who has the best
hand that wins it's who makes everyone
else think that they have the best hand
and right there's there's a lot that
goes on than that and so because it's a
zero-sum game right that if my win does
not equal your win my win is going to
equal some other players losses then I
have an incentive to dis inform you
where information about reality is a
source of competitive advantage this is
actually the real kind of key way of
thinking about because disinformation
even happens in nature with other
animals you'll see a caterpillar that
evolved to have something on its tail
that looks like a head to dis inform
birds so that they go to pick up the
false head and it might still be able to
live right like that's actually an
involved disinformation strategy and
it's just that the disinformation in
nature happens very slowly and where the
selective pressures on the side of the
caterpillar and the bird or coevolving
right so the bird is getting better at
noticing those things as the caterpillar
is getting better at dealing with that
camouflage is a kind of disinformation
right it's an attempt to not signal
something fully because there's rival
risk dynamics between the caterpillar
and the bird in that scenario but with
people with our abstract replicators we
can create the distortion much much much
faster we can have a symmetries in the
capacity to create the distortion and
even exponential asymmetries and so it's
actually really quite different so you
think about the poker bluff and you
think about like even in soccer or
football when someone fakes left and
then goes right that's a disinformation
strategy where if we're competing in
information about the nature of reality
where the water is where the gold is
what the market is going to do next if
this company is going to make it
whatever equals a source of advantage
but we're an assumed rival risk dynamic
we're competing for the same money
competing for the same attention
whatever then first I have
the incentive to withhold information
right so I don't want to tell you where
the gold is or I don't want you to know
the intellectual property that I'm going
to monetize simply the withholding of
information fuck's up the information
ecology so much because I'm doing cancer
research and I've had some big
breakthroughs but I'm not trying to
share that with everyone else just doing
cancer research because this is being
funded by a for-profit process that
needs to be able to monetize that
intellectual property right and so we
can see how much problem happens as a
result of withholding of information but
we can also see how intractable this
problem seems within a game theoretic
environment like capitalism right I keep
saying capitalism I'm not going to say
that any other bad economic system we've
ever tried is the answer because they
aren't we have basis for disinformation
and communism and socialism and fascism
we're gonna suggest that new structures
that have not ever happened are needed
I'm just wanting to say that here so
people don't attach to me criticizing
capitalism is probably going to suggest
something that doesn't work so the first
thing is withholding information and we
see in business how much focus is on IP
and NDA's and you know those types of
things but then it's not simply
withholding information it's also
dissing forming right just like the
poker bluff for the fake left and go
right we have an instant and we can see
in warfare we try and have black
projects where we withhold the
information because we don't want the
other side to know what our military
capacities are but we also try to dis
inform what our military capacities are
or where we're gonna attack or whatever
else as a source of advantage that's
been happening forever sons who writes
about that right I mean it's just we've
we've had a basis for disinformation for
a long time we've had rival risk
dynamics for a long time the rival risk
dynamics are a basis by which we can get
ahead by war and killing somebody else
or lying to them right or ruining the
Commons
it's just exponential tech leads to with
those same incentives leads to
exponential disinformation
exponential extraction exponential
pollution exponential the scaled warfare
and on a finite playing field that
self-destruct so the underlying cause is
the same stuff that's been happening but
at a speed and scope and scale and level
of complexity that forces us to have to
actually deal with the underlying
structures now because they they can't
continue okay so that's the game
theoretic side of it now what would it
take to have an intact information
ecology where any information that
anyone had just on the truthfulness side
was being shared there was no incentive
for disinformation first let's just
imagine that array like no
disinformation let's give some other
examples of disinformation there's not
just where I'm intentionally trying to
mislead you there's also where I'm
sharing signal for some purpose for me
that might mislead you in it I'm not
intending to I just don't care if I do
so let's say there I want some increased
attention and this might be because I'm
going to monetize that attention might
be because I'm going to get political
power might be simply because I just
want attention right so let's say I
comment on what some famous person is
doing let's say I disagree with him I'm
instantly going to get some attention if
I critique them effectively that I
didn't necessarily earn and I don't even
have to believe the critique because via
Association of that type I'm going to
get some attention so now people have a
basis to focus on something they weren't
focused on before to criticize it
because that will get attention or to
compliment it or to play off of it in a
way that is not actually what they care
about or believe and again you look at
how liquidus it is you know that kind of
phenomenon all right so the answer to
getting over the truthfulness issue is
actually post game theoretic world
because which is the same answers like
how do we get past warfare well it's not
just kinetic warfare where we throw
bombs or rocks at each other it's also
info warfare and narrative warfare and
economic warfare right which is
basically any in-group that is
coordinating to compete against an
out-group in some kind of zero-sum
dynamic and that's companies to
companies its companies to people it's
people to people it's countries to
countries its global economic trading
Blox with each other it's all of those
things what can people do right now
within a game theoretic world to start
to create spaces of truthfulness start
to create relationships where one of the
highest values is truthfulness with
other people that are capable of and
want and are committed to that where
people are not only not lying to each
other but they are endeavouring to not
withhold information which is tremendous
intimacy and tremendous vulnerability
and see if you can create enough
psychological safety with some people to
be able to start exploring what does it
mean to actually share information
honestly so that we can have that and
all kind of make sense together that's
one thing and there's also something
where it's like if you don't throw trash
out the window of your car because you
don't pollute the environment be careful
about not polluting the information
ecology by rationalizing why your own
miss or disinformation is okay and just
start to think of it that way think of
anytime you're sharing a little lies as
as polluting the information ecology and
being like oh wow I don't want to do
that I would I don't want to be part of
the fucked up information ecology okay
so now on the true side which is not
just a mapping or a correspondence
between what I'm saying and what I think
but between what I'm saying and what
shared reality is which means there has
to be a correspondence between what I
think in reality that means I had to do
since making well before I share
something right so this is the topic of
a pistol
so one is movement past game theory
the next is epistemology how do we know
stuff so even if nobody was lying and
withholding information the complexity
of the world makes a epistemology hard
and most people aren't even endeavoring
at it so I have if no one was lying and
I could take all the information as at
least truthful there would be certain
epistemic processes that I could apply
that I can't apply if I can't even take
the sources of signal as being signal
without a lot of noise right so there's
epistemology that I have to have within
the context of an inn of an environment
has a lot of disinformation how do I
make sense of what is true and what
isn't true about signal coming in and
then how do i parse from lots of Sigma
what might be true about reality and for
like to just get a sense of why like how
big a deal this is you take any of the
biggest issues in the world like the
issues that could determine whether or
not we keep existing as a species okay
so take big environmental issues like
climate change there's disagreement as
to whether climate change is relieved in
a thing and to the extent that it is a
thing what the causes are and what the
time skills are now most people who
believe fervently no climate change is
real 97% of climate scientists agree
it's anthropogenic greenhouse gases etc
most of the people that believe that
fervently enough to kind of like go into
narrative warfare for it have never
actually looked at the primary data
deeply themselves and yet there's an
almost religious fervor around it that
was based on having proxied their sense
making the people who they believe so
the UN's headed or the Gates Foundation
said it or whatever it is I've heard it
repeated enough times just just through
repeatability like I have been
programmed to believe this thing is true
which is not that different than
believing a fundamentalist religion
religious ideal right and let's say we
take people's fervent ideas on vaccines
or their fervent ideas on the viability
of market ideology or almost anything
like that almost no one who has fervent
ideas has a good epistemic basis for the
level of certainty they hold there's a
decoupling between how much certain team
they have and how much certainty they
should have through right process and
then you look at who are they proxying
their sense making - in most the time
they're not even proxying their sense
making to the people who did the
original research many of whom disagree
with each other and were funded by
somebody to say something that is not
fully true in the first place and who
maybe were employing epistemic biases
themselves but typically it's somebody
else who looked at all of that and then
someone else who looked at all of that
so you might have like a bunch of
climate scientists into someone who is
speaking about that as a client's
climate scientists at a more synthetic
level like a James Hansen or whatever -
then like a Gore or someone who is
actually speaking to the public who were
proxying our sense making - and we say
okay how many steps removed is it and
how good was the original data and so if
we think about okay how much radiation
actually was released into the
environment from Fukushima it seems like
a very straightforward thing take a
Geiger counter and go out and do the
studies but how many people are equipped
to take a Geiger counter out and go do
that or to be able to actually pay
attention to how the flow dynamics and
the air and the water are gonna work or
you know so many things and so we have
to take other people's data to begin
with and those other people let's say
the data was the Japanese government or
TEPCO or whoever it was or it can
a conspiracy theory group that is saying
no no it's actually releasing huge
amounts of ocean all the fish are
totally toxified but they might just be
they have a basis to dis inform because
they're getting viewership that they're
monetizing through that what how the
fuck do we make sense of it right so we
what we start to get is it's like is AI
gonna solve a bunch of problems and be
relatively safe or is AI the biggest
risk and going to kill us and you see
the you see kind of fervent disagreement
but you see a still pedal-to-the-metal
going as fast forward as we can with AI
and with CRISPR biotech and with every
type of exponential technology that
could be catastrophic and and so there's
increasing speed of choice making with
decreasing sense-making and to just
think about like okay
or even what's really going on with the
Chinese government and its cyber warfare
relationship of the US government and
with kind of the what its actual
capacities are and what its intent and
agency is and those types of issues well
we know that's going to be obscured we
know both sides and all kinds of sites
are gonna be obscuring information and
it gets even worse because it's not just
that you've got this group of people
called China and this group of people
called the US and that they're in a game
theoretic relationship with each other
but everybody on Team USA cooperates
perfectly you know of course it's not
that right so even within the
intelligence agencies I might have two
different intelligence agencies that are
supposed to be cooperating but they're
competing for a bigger percentage of
black-budget
and so they might be withholding
information from each other or even dis
informing each other then I might have
two agents within an agency competing
for the same promotion who might run
disinfo on each other so I have fractal
disinformation right at almost every
place because of a game theory at a
consent of system which is the balance
sheet of countries the balance sheet of
organizations the balance sheet of all
the way down to individual people right
this separation of the of agency
- now I'm back to a game theory truth on
the side but I have to factor that when
I'm trying to make sense of things
because I have to be able to parse
signal from noise to then be able to
synthesize the signal but then even if
that wasn't the case I'm just just
trying to do a pistol mala Jeon good
signal and I have to say ok in a complex
system like we're we can't even forecast
the weather ten days out very well how
do i forecast the effect of putting
certain kinds of pesticides or
genetically modified organisms or
whatever into the environments right
it's a complex system that we can't
forecast very well at all we we don't we
don't know the tiniest bit of the actual
information of how that complex system
is going to regulate but we're going to
do stuff that affects those systems at
scale what is the right epistemology to
be able to make sense of is this a good
choice and so you can see and we know
what are all the metrics we have to
factor let's say we're talking about
biotech ok so I can give you a drug that
is good for some biometric that happens
to be associated with the disease that
I'm taking I'm trying to get the doctors
to be able to use this drug allowed by
the FDA to treat a particular disease
and then since the disease is identified
by this biomarker I have to affect this
biomarker so let's say I'm talking about
high cholesterol and so we develop a
statin for it how many other metrics are
this is the statin effecting well every
day we're learning new biometrics we
didn't even know existed how many of
those are being affected they're part of
the unknown unknown set that we don't
even know to be able to do risk
calculation on now we could say well
let's run the experiment long enough
before we release the drug to see if it
affects total longevity and all cause
mortality well nobody fucking does that
nobody's gonna run a hundred year
experiments on something before they
release the thing they're gonna run the
shortest ones they can so we're you have
a system that has delayed causation how
do I know if that's creating problems
way down the road well it does all the
time
right so we get rid of DDT or parathion
or malathion because we see that it's
super poisonous after we've been
spraying it on everybody and then we
bring in a new drug that we also didn't
do long term Studies on I mean a new
pesticide
and then we outlaw it after a little
while and then we bring in new one the
new ones aren't safer they just haven't
had as much time to show how dangerous
they are so then the question is like
what would the right epistemology be how
many metrics do I have to factor how do
I know how to factor those metrics what
is the total information complexity of
the scenario relative to how much I have
actually the information complexity of
the assessment that we've done so we can
get into at some depth the topic of
appropriate epistemology for various
contexts but the I guess the first thing
I can say is that if people aren't even
thinking about that their chance of
making sense well is pretty close to
zero if we think about the concept of a
meme the way that Dawkins originally put
it forward it's a abstract pattern
replicator where a gene is an
instantiated pattern replicator which
means that it can mutate and change and
affect behavior and propagate much much
much faster right and we can kind of say
that in Homo sapiens our genetics
selected for memetics for higher-order
mimetics right our genetics because most
other species what the selective
pressures had them be adaptive to an
environment right they there's mutation
and then the mutations that survive and
make the best are the ones that make it
through but that's within the context of
survive in that environment and are able
to mate successfully in that environment
so they become more more fit to their
environment so the cheetah does really
well in the savanna I would not do well
in the Arctic and the polar bear
wouldn't do wellness it in an orca
wouldn't do well outside of the ocean
right like so they they are well adapt
to their environment because of our
abstraction capacity which is both our
capacity for language and memes as well
as tools we were able to go and become
adaptive become actually apex predators
in the savanna and in the Arctic and in
the ocean and everywhere right we were
able to go to every environment which
means that as soon as our population
would normally if we were any other
animals
to level off in relationship with the
environmental carrying capacity of an
environment we just moved we were able
to decimate that environment and move to
the next one right into all of them and
then but that part isn't the part I want
to get into it now
it's that since we were gonna be
adaptive to totally new environments and
since we were gonna create tools where
what it was to be adaptive was changing
sin since we modify our environment in
ways the other animals don't we can't
come in genetically fit to a specific
environment we have to come in and be
able to imprint the environment that
we're in so we know how to be fit two
totally different environments cuz like
it's not that adaptive for us to throw
Spears or even climb trees all that well
but it is to be able to like text and
drive and stuff that wouldn't have been
adaptive thousand years ago at all and
so this is why human babies are
embryonic or jnanis for so long right
compared to any other animal if you like
the thing I like to do here is to think
about a horse standing up in like 20
minutes and a human being able to walk
in like a year and just think about how
many 20 minute segments multiplied into
a year to get a sense of how much longer
we are helpless than anything else is
and even amongst the other primates
close to us is there's really nothing
like us in terms of the extended
helplessness and that's because we're we
don't have inherited knowledge of how to
be us since the environment is going to
be different we have to imprint the
environment that we're in to be able to
be adaptive to environments that we're
changing right so and so this is a
saying that our genetics selected for
neuroplasticity selected for memetics
our hardware selected for faster
software updates that could have faster
changes in adaptive basis so that we
could move our environments and all
those types of things so if we think
about a meat and kind of like a gene as
an ax pattern replicator but as an
abstract pattern replicator that can
mutate much quicker there's also a big
differences that the other animals are
it in an environment the mutation across
genes is very evenly distributed
mutations happening to the gazelles and
to the cheetahs at an equal rate right
and there's Co selective pressures on
both of them so they're both getting
faster the slowest ones of each are
dying off and so there's this kind of
symmetry of power that has the
competitive pressures between them have
them all up level but when we start
being mostly mimetic and the other
species are still mostly genetic meaning
we're largely based we're getting
adaptive based on abstract pattern
replicators are still in stan see a
pattern replicators we can increase our
per date of capacity much faster than
they can increase their than the
environment can increase its resilience
to our creative capacity which means
that we can debase the whole substrate
that we depend upon which is self
terminating right you can't keep
debasing that which you depend upon so
in evolution there is a selection
process for the genes that make it
through right but they there is this
kind of symmetry of the genes that make
it through because of the evenness of
mutation and because of the co selective
pressures now with mimetics the memes
that make it through are the memes that
win in a rival risk context not the ones
that necessarily represents the true or
the good or the beautiful so the
propagated memes propagate more than the
true memes propagate this is a super
important concept to understand which is
like I was always dumbfounded thinking
about the evolution of religions take
Christianity for instance and you say
okay so Jesus when they brought Mary
Magdalene said let he who has no
sentence amongst you cast the first
stone right and then when they're
nailing him up he says Father forgive
them for they know not what they they do
and he's like bringing forgiveness to
Judaism and in his name we did the
Crusades in the Inquisition and said we
will not just kill but torture anyone
who doesn't accept the Lord of peace is
there like how the fuck did we do that
how did we do the mental gymnastics
to take the guy whose key teachings were
forgiveness and torture people in the
name of that well we figured out how to
do it right but the key is that we was
super adaptive so you you've got an idea
right say you've got Jesus teachings or
we can take it in any of them and then
there's going to be a bunch of mutations
on that idea different interpretations
of it some of the mutations say be quiet
and don't push your ideas on anyone like
be contemplative and you know etc and
those ones don't catch on because they
aren't being intentionally propagated
and other ones say go out and propagate
these ideas on missions and on Crusades
and focus on the not the forgiveness
parts but on the like wrath and
Leviticus and who God's enemies we're
like focus on those parts and that you
actually get better spots in heaven for
converting more people right and and so
what you end up getting is that the
ideas that catch on are the ones that
win and narrative warfare but they're
having to catch on so then say Islam is
also competing for some of the same
people right because ultimately the
religions become the basis of in groups
that are competing against out groups
for fundamentally political and economic
and survival type basis so I can hold
people together with a political left or
political right ideology or a capitalist
communist ideology or racial identity
ideology or religious ideologies all of
those become the basis of an in-group
that can be that can bind together to be
more successful in competition with
assumed out groups right but what that
means is that rival risk game theoretic
environment is going to be selecting for
what is effective at rivalry not what is
true and and definitely not what is good
for the whole and the moment that
anybody figures something out that is
more effective at rivalry than everybody
else reverse engineers it and you know
creates similar mimetic mutations on
other sides and so there's not that many
James right there they're lovely people
right and totally nonviolent and
aren't you know aren't gonna hurt
anybody but they're also not pushing
their ideas on anybody so the ideas
aren't spreading that fast so the ideas
that have an artificial focus on the
spreading of ideas and figure out how to
emotionally manipulate people into
believing the idea with heaven and hell
and whatever right are going to spread
more so this is a key thing to get is
you know whether we're taking it it's
not just right I'm giving the example of
the teachings of Jesus turning into the
Crusades or the Inquisition but it's
also take thinking like Darwin right so
take the context in which Darwin came
about Darwin came about just following
Malthus right so so we got the British
Empire's first kind of real world ruling
Empire first time that a global
inventory of resources was ever
conducted
Malthus came up with the fundamental
principle of scarcity or inadequacy says
hey people are reproducing geometrically
resources reproduce her thematically
there's not going to be enough for
everybody not everybody's gonna make it
well then who's gonna make it fuck that
idea says compassion is not viable we
can't all make it fundamentally
mathematically there aren't the
resources for now this is gibberish
actually today because we know that
populations don't reproduce
exponentially forever
they steady-state and we've already seen
the population in Japan and in Denmark
and another like the most economically
successful countries start decreasing
right and we also know that we can
recycle resources we don't have to just
have a linear materials economy where we
use them up and turn them into trash and
that completely fundamentally changes
the underlying scarcity basis we can
also share resources in different ways
so the underlying thinking behind
Malthus isn't true but he didn't know
that at the time it seemed quite
compelling
so then we say okay so fuck a solution
for everyone a world that works for all
is not even viable those who want it are
simply not facing up to reality and so
if not everyone's gonna make it who's
going to and so then Darwin comes out in
that context and so the idea of survival
of the fittest is the idea we focus on
the most even though that's not
that he emphasized early in the writing
hardly at all right and so there was
again taking Darwin's idea in one
context and then also taking the most
propagated version of it that led to
social Darwinism that basically reified
institutional sociopathy right which is
okay well if not everybody's gonna make
it some people are gonna be like
predators other people are gonna be like
prey predators don't feel bad when prey
died you have to actually call the herd
sometimes like there and if you start to
think about how hierarchical power
structures work to get to the top of a
hierarchical power structure like a big
corporation or a government or a
religion that's structured that way
let's leave that one off for a moment
just say corporation or government I
have to win at a lot of win-lose games I
have to get the promotion over or win at
the campaign over other people where
zero something somebody wins somebody
loses right so the top is going to be
people who were best at winning out win
those games so it's actually going to so
if I have a lot of empathy and I don't
want and I actually care about other
people's loss I'm gonna do less well if
I'm a sociopath and don't give a shit
about it I'm gonna do better at that if
I'm willing to dis inform to get ahead
I'll do better at so this is why we see
higher percentage of sociopaths and
Psychopaths as CEOs and in the normal
distribution of population which also
means that the people have the most
influence in the world are
asymmetrically empowered and
asymmetrically sociopathic but the way
that we interpreted Darwin was to was
reifying that as a reasonable thing and
even a good thing so we have to
recognize that any idea even if it
started as true or good or beautiful
gets put into the game theoretic mill
right and what comes what propagates is
the thing that's propagated so why do
bad ideas catch on like largely for this
reason so oftentimes the best ideas are
not well marketed and aren't even easily
marketable and
best marketed ideas that are gonna catch
on the most are not that true and pretty
shitty results so this is again
something that people have to really pay
attention to is I think Jordan in one of
his interviews with you talked about the
difference between real thinking and
simulated thinking so if I'm just taking
memes that I've heard I'm in a
conversation and I'm listening for which
of the things I'm gonna say that I have
heard somewhere else I'm basically a
meme propagator it's not real thinking
right I'm not actually endeavoring to
try to make sense of the world in a new
way that I've never done before most
people hear something here a meme that
comes in and because it's from Fox they
believe it or don't believe it or
because it's from CNN or whatever it is
they believe it or don't believe it so
they basically have some cluster of
memes that creates like a memetic immune
system that says which idea is to accept
and which one's to reject and then once
it's accepted then propagates them
that's not thinking and there's no
sovereignty in that and groups that have
asymmetric mean broadcast capacity are
good at making memes that are sticky
customized to specific audiences and
being able to split test uptake right
and then being able to you know then you
get into high tech things like Facebook
and it's like okay I can actually pay
attention to what you click on and do
profoundly deep analytics I can pay
attention to mouse hover I can pay
attention to all these types of
analytics and customize the
disinformation to everybody using the
kind of AI that beats the best chess
players in the world of chess right this
is stuff that Tristan Harris talks about
and so the AI that beats Kasparov at
chess easily it'll nobody is as good at
being strategic with themselves as
Kasparov is a chess and we don't even
know that we're engaged in that and yet
it's competing with us for our attention
for the its purpose of maximize time
on-site now it just happens to be that
I'm gonna scroll and bounce unless
than catches my attention short things
will catch my attention more because I'm
in a hurry
so just orientation for small bit size
makes everyone more fundamentalists with
shittier attention spans and then if the
headline is more kind of sensational
it's going to attract attention more so
then we get these big platforms that
don't want to make people
fundamentalists or how to drive politics
but they do simply as a byproduct of the
fact that limbic hijacks are sticky and
they're optimizing for time on sight
so first thing is that individual memes
don't get selected for mean memes
interrelate with other memes to create
world views because I usually can't make
a choice based on a meet and I have to
make a choice based on a representation
of the world just going to be a bunch of
ideas write a bunch of memes a bunch of
data and so we get these kind of meme
complexes and so we can think about the
evolution of meme complexes so let's go
ahead and look at like the evolution of
religious ideas we can look at the
evolution of political ideas or anything
scientific ideas so religious ideas so
you'll have some kind of central meme
but then you'll also have protector
memes that emerge with it that also
believing them protects against the kind
of cognitive processes that could have
someone stop believing the primary mean
because if the primary intent last so
the question isn't just what makes a
meme propagate but also what makes it
endure and resist change so there's the
evolution of memes but also they're the
mean complexes resilience in the
presence of other competing meme
complexes right so we'll give these
protector memes and then we'll also give
propagator memes that are trying to take
the whole complex and propagate it so
there's there's a whole football team of
defense and offense and carrying the
ball and right like that happens so
let's say we
get some kind of fundamentalist religion
so let's say we we look at Christianity
this would be the same for any religion
this just probably the one that most
people here will relate to so you'll
have some kind of central doctrinal
teachings about Christ and God and what
good is and those types of things but
then protector memes are what could make
me not believe these things and how do
we protect against those processes so if
we want to have say a literal
interpretation then we don't want people
to doubt the literal interpretation then
we start to have things memes like faith
is something God likes and doubt which
is another term for critical thinking is
something that God doesn't like it
actually comes from the devil and you'll
burn in hell for it and so the more that
you just believe in the teaching the
better your chances of heaven are and
the more good you are and the more that
you doubt it the more that Satan
actually got to you right so that's a
very strong protector meme against the
kind of critical thinking that could
make you question the basis of the
religion you'll also have other
protector memes like if I believe this
if I continue to believe this I get to
keep having a family and a community
that will take care of me if I'm poor
and if I'm sick and you know will help
me out in times of warfare and all those
things and if I stop everybody will
disown me or to various degree is that
like there will be direct implications
to my life regarding the change in these
beliefs and then again you'll have
propagator memes we need to go on
mission and share the good word with
other people and convert them so you
start to see a memetic ecosystem so now
if I've got propagator memes coming up
against some some people who also have
protector memes from a previous complex
then there's an evolution there's a
competition of which memes are more
successful so then we look at the kind
of
illusion of the types of mean complexes
over time now there other people have a
lot more expertise in this than I do and
I don't have adequately detailed history
to say this is a Rea historical
narrative it's an example of the type of
thing that could happen right so ticket
is that so say you look at the evolution
of the concept of Hell right Hell as a
mean in Western traditions so first say
you take Eastern traditions like
Hinduism or Buddhism they might have
many different hell realms and nobody
stays in any of them forever
right like most of the interpretations
have everybody gets to moksha or
liberation eventually these are places
that people go to learn things as part
of the liberation path so and if you
look at the descriptions of Hell at
various points in Christianity hell got
nastier as time went on and God also got
more authoritarian and heaven got better
and even if we go before that we look in
early cultures and we see most early
cultures were animistic right the spirit
of the Buffalo and of the tree and of
the river and there was the spirit of
everything and so spirit was radically
decentralized and then there was an
evolution because of evolutionary
pressures on memes that correspondent
with little tribes living in nature too
early civilizations there is an
evolution to polytheism which is now not
the spirit of everything but some
smaller number of more powerful spirit
or gods right so there's starts to be a
consolidation of power in the religion
corresponding to a consolidation of
actual power and the social structures
that are happening and the way that we
make sense of the world in the way that
the religious idea actually supports the
thing that we're doing in the politics
and like that right and then we end up
going from polytheism to monotheism and
if you think about control systems right
some few being able to control a mini in
ways that are better for the few than
they are for the many and how you have
systems of kind of
institutional controller oppression so
if we're having consolidation for having
increasing power inequality in our
social systems and we want to justify
that increasing power inequality having
and we want to justify increasing
authoritarian power having gods that
reflect that is valuable those memes are
gonna actually be adaptive to the social
systems doing that right and if you
think about an authority that controls a
population with reward and Punishment
and then we make we actually make a God
in our image and we say okay well what
would the infinite Authority be and what
would infinite reward an infinite
punishment and you just take all the
concepts to their logical zenith that's
what Christianity did right so you have
one all-powerful God beyond reproach
with an infinite punishment and an
infinite eternal punishment an infinite
reward if you're trying to look for
maximum behavior mod that's what you end
up coming to but it's almost like the
strange attractor of a landscape that
just takes it to zenith right where it's
so terrifying once you've been
indoctrinated leave that belief system
because if it because hell is so bad
that any chance of it is so unacceptable
that all kind of do Pascal's wager and
just stay in it just because right now
of course by believing that I might be
going to the Muslim hell if they're true
but that never got its hooks in me when
I was young so I'm not as afraid of it
unless I grew up there in which case it
has the hooks and I'm much more afraid
of that than I am of the Christian hell
so we can see that you get an evolution
of the gods getting more powerful and
more authoritarian and more propagated
and more ideology around propagation and
reward and punishment and like those
things that you would expect that that
and specifically it's that the groups
that instantiated those memes would have
actually done better in a natural
selection determined in more fair
then and and also if I have a man's
dominion over Earth ideology it says yes
destroying the environment for us and
it's okay if we destroy the environment
because God's gonna come back and remake
everything you know after purgatory
anyways and and treating animals badly
really doesn't matter because again
dominion over like those ideas are
actually going to be adaptive in terms
of increasing the game of power even
though they're if you take to zenith
that game itself terminates it destroys
the whole world on the substrate that we
depend upon so you want to think about
and we can see that there there's like
so we're looking at a kind of Christian
worldview right but you can see that a
whole worldview of ideas comes up around
supporting Trump or climate change or
critical thinking and Dawkins kind of
scientific materialism or each of those
worldviews have processes of doing of
in-group out-group pressures right like
you'll be something bad will happen if
you don't believe these things going to
hell is the worst example but simply
being rejected by the in-group and being
called like a stupid conspiracy theorist
or a pseudo scientist or an anti Beck's
or whatever it is that you know or
infidel it goes against whatever the the
in-group idea is there's a strong
selective pressure to defect on our own
thinking to the center of the in-group
and a lot of advantage will occur if I
defect on my own sense making to a
center of the in-group and it's not I
don't trust my own sense making so I'd
rather be part of an in-group or at
least I'll be safe by being part of an
in-group and I can't actually because I
can't make sense of the world and I
can't take care of myself really in the
present blip and it's not safe to
disagree with everybody right if I share
views that just have me disagree with
everybody and I don't have any in-group
than I seem fucked so what I do is I
look at which in group seems to be
closest to what I think and then I
defect on my thinking to normal
the in-group right so we want to just
kind of pay attention to you know
looking at these different information
ecosystems mimetic ecosystems to seeing
how they evolve into how they apply in
group out group types of selective
pressures and how they apply appeal
other than go to pista mala G right like
how they apply rhetorical skills and
emotional manipulation skills to compel
people to believe something where the
basis to believe it should actually be
some better epistemic process then the
key thing is if we can start noticing
this in our self and noticing where we
feel a kind of bias towards or away from
something before we've thought about it
well based on how it fits with the rest
of our mimetic complex that we also
haven't analyzed well I guess a lot of
people a lot of people might be tempted
just to give up on trying to make sense
of the world I think almost everyone has
again it's like it's Fukushima still in
risk of further breakdown or not has it
already polluted the ocean should we not
be eating fish from the Pacific or not
is 5g actually possibly a problem or not
is climate change and coral reef die-off
and eminent issue in the next five years
or not and if so what is the right way
to approach it are we approaching our
own doom with CRISPR with AI like these
are seriously important things to have
some clarity on right these are things
that we actually want to come to enough
certainty on to make choices because we
are making choices and by not making
choices we're making choices by default
in terms the face of what market
pressures are are doing and almost
everyone if they really kind of think
about it will admit I actually don't
know the answer to any of those things
but that doesn't slow down the rate of
first to market for powerful AI or you
know what anything else right and to the
degree that people don't admit that they
have no idea and they think they have an
idea if they're honest most of them will
say I'm pretty sure I have an idea
because I proxied my sense making to
other people that I trusted but I didn't
actually do the foundational research
and to the degree that people did the
foundational research if they're honest
enough they'll say the total amount of
data that I looked at relative to the
complexity of the scenario was orders of
magnitude too small so most people have
given up on sense making about based
reality they just have an admitted bit
weight where I can get ahead in a human
ecosystem by affecting what other people
believe independent of what is true
independent of base reality then we live
in a simulated reality where if I can if
I can get you to believe something that
will lead you to vote in my interest or
to purchase things in my interest or
whatever game theory will have me try to
optimize distortion and optimize my
ability to get ahead at creating and
winning at simulations and it won't have
me try to connect to base reality at all
right and so we we get a world that is
so constructed and decoupled from base
reality that most of the time what is
true isn't even relevant and it's even
further than that it's that there's a
whole class of people for whom the idea
that there are true concepts doesn't
even appeal to them very much now some
people might think this sounds like
excessively cynical or but okay I'm
gonna be careful with this because I
don't want to say names that will create
conflict unnecessarily but I was talking
to someone the other day who was saying
that what I believe is
give or take the same as what this other
person believes and what we believe on
this topic couldn't be more
diametrically opposite and but the the
person who is saying yeah you know we
all kind of are on the same page we all
believe the same thing wanted to put on
an event where we would all be there
that she would sell lots of tickets for
and and her orientation is what is
actually going to optimize viewership
and so how do we get people that are
going to be engaging mix with people who
are famous enough whatever talk to Mai's
viewership in and I was focused on what
is actually true do we are we being
earnest and what we're endeavoring to do
here and her sense that we believe kind
of the same thing because like we both
talked about technology and we both
talked about the future and we both kind
of want stuff to be good and we both use
the word exponential sometimes it wasn't
that she actually thinks that what I
think is true or what this other person
thinks is true she doesn't it's that the
idea of true beliefs is not what she's
optimizing for what she's optimizing for
is what's gonna get the most views and
then there's a backfill a rational
backfill that said that tries to
rationalize that it's we we believe kind
of the same thing or whatever
but the orientation isn't even trying to
say do I believe what this person saying
it's saying do I believe that I can make
money on what this person is saying
so you realize that we live so much in a
simulated reality it like if I'm a
venture capitalist I can make money on a
product that is shittier than products
that currently exist even though the
market is supposed to be a sense making
mechanism within the context of demand
that there will be mutation right lots
of different versions of the same
product for the same service and that
the one that's actually the best at the
best price is the one that the market
will select for and it'll be upregulated
that's kind of so the first part was
mutation then survival selection and
then good parts of a few different ones
might combine and that's kind of mate
selection right that's kind of how we
think of markets as a sense making
system lines of evolutionary theory but
we all know that the best marketed
product will oftentimes beat the actual
best product where the price of product
development drops the price of marketing
and customer acquisition goes up which
means that it's a shittier product
better marketed that means the sense
making system is broken right it's not a
good sense making system so but as a
venture capitalist I can invest in a
company that I know is going to create a
massive distortion level and market
really successfully and maybe the
company will go bankrupt at some later
point but I will have exited by then so
I don't really care
long term I care that it's gonna market
successfully and be successful
financially not if it's actually a
better product or service and so if the
if the CEO is a really compelling
sociopath that is highly motivated and
spins distortion bubbles I'm going to be
more motivated by that than thinking
that the product is actually
fundamentally novel II better in many
cases right it's not only story but thus
a story and so then my goal is to
actually invest in someone else's
ability to generate a distortion bubble
that will pull enough people along that
me as an early investor it'll lead to
adoption of customers and other
investors and then I exit before the
distortion bubble pops right and so we
can see like there are whole domains
that are fairly decoupled from reality
from base reality we're spinning
simulated realities is the whole goal
and so a lot of people her it's another
thing we have to pay attention to is
that the cognitive complexity of a lot
of the issues we face is just much
faster than most people have time for
then most people have training for and
even vaster than we evolved to process
so this idea of hyper objects right that
there's not just plutonium but all of
the plutonium or all of climate change
or all of species extinction or whatever
I can't actually observe that directly
but I can infer it know that it's a real
thing but how do I hold the cognitive
complexity of any of those let alone all
of them right as it is a very tricky
thing and but I still have to feed my
kids and pay the bills tomorrow
and so the adaptive pressures on me are
to focus on what I need to focus on in
the very small and in the short term
even though what I'm doing because of
globalized supply chains is affecting
the global in the long term the idea
think globally act locally most of us
are doing the opposite right we're
actually thinking very locally about
having actions that affect the world
globally which means we're we're
thinking on very short timescales fairly
narcissistic self-indulgent and you know
timescales but with things that will
have enduring and massive impact and
that is a decoupling of scale it's a
decoupling of sense making and choice
making a bunch of things but so for most
people the idea of having the luxury of
trying to make sense of the world is
something they don't even feel like they
have because they're nose-down just
trying to like do the next couple things
they have to do and then other people
who are actually trying to get ahead are
optimizing for simulations and
distortion bubbles rather than trying to
make sense of the world so there's a lot
of people who aren't actually even
trying to make sense of the world now
when I ask what is meaningful what is
meaningful is going to be bound to what
I think is real and if I give up on
knowing what is real there's a way in
which I'm giving up on the depth of my
connectedness to what's meaningful so
yes giving up on sense making there's a
is kind of an expression of a type of
nihilism and it and it feeds into
further nihilism first thing is I stop
trying to squish reality into a
perspective this is super important and
then anytime I have a perspective and I
am defaulting into thinking of it as the
truth I become dubious of that in myself
and they become curious about the
partial truth in other people's
perspectives including the ones that I
think are stupid and crazy right because
they none of them have no signal even if
I think there's a lot of noise so I want
to say why do they think it is true well
this bias that bias okayed all that and
some perception mixed with the bias what
is the per what are they perceiving that
then with the bias is also there maybe
it's not that much sense making but it's
something that's meaningful right so
this is st. Francis's quote of seek more
to understand them to be understood
right seek first to understand that
means actually seek to take different
perspectives so the Hegelian dialectic
is you've got a thesis and then the
antithesis I actually want to try and
take this perspective and construct this
case and once I've constructed both of
these now I'm stuck with either that I
flip-flop between them or I'm just
confused or I just claim paradox or the
next step is thesis antithesis synthesis
there's a higher-order truth it is
actually not paradoxical that reconciles
them it just requires a higher order of
complexity it's paradoxical within too
low a level of complexity Einsteins you
can't solve a problem at the level of
problem at the level of complexity and
so since to how
is three-dimensional no two-dimensional
picture will actually give me a solid
sense on it if I'm looking at the
cylinder we talked about this the other
night if I'm trying to collapse the
cylinder by a dimension and take a
cylinder which is a three dimensional
object and take a 2d slice of it if I
got a cylinder like this a slice like
this is a circle a slice like this is a
rectangle in 2d circle and rectangle are
mutually exclusive descriptions of a
shape one has straight lines and corners
the other has no straight lines and no
corners if I try to say well it's both
that just makes no sense at all right if
I say well it must be part of both so
it's a rounded rectangle well that it
has no truth at all but I have to
actually be able to construct a higher
dimensional space in which rectangle
nough sand circle misfit together in a
way that is makes perfect sense called
it cylinder but this is what a level of
consciousness that isn't the level that
caused the problem the problem is
partiality of perspective that can
create then a basis for conflict right
so then there is a higher order that is
able to reconcile those and so seeking
that and this is where you know we're
seeking clarity more than simplicity
because the simplicity can happen
through reduction right and typically
the synthesis comes from novel insight
that neither the thesis nor the
antithesis held it's not just well it's
a little bit of both so a couple
examples let's say we take kind of
political left and political radiology
there's a gazillion examples and what we
call the political left and right today
might seem actually quite different than
what it was in the past so let's take a
kind of what had previous to recently
been kind of some essential ideas and
Republican or Democrat platforms so we
kind of have this Republican right
oriented idea of wanting to empower the
self responsibility and sovereignty of
the individual and more individualistic
and so smaller government less social
services more empowering of those who
are on
snoring and pull themselves up by their
bootstraps and you know that kind of
thing and then you have the kind of more
democratic left perspective that says
well and here it's saying the collective
is actually created by the individual so
we want to empower the individuals that
are creative and take agency because
better individuals make a better whole
that's kind of the gist over here it's
like well but the individuals are being
conditioned by the environment that
they're born into by the whole and so
even though I can't find that one story
of that one guy who pulled themselves up
by the bootstraps in the ghetto there's
a whole lot more people that succeeded
who were born into the Hamptons and born
into South Central and so let's create
better environments that actually
condition better people because there's
top-down effects the holes create
affecting the individuals so there's
there's for many people some seemingly
compelling truth in both of these and
also problems right so there can be a
right oriented perspective that says hey
look if we set up social services in
welfare and whatever we actually
condition shittier people who are less
strong and resilient in the face of the
environment we D incentivize those who
are most entrepreneur and creative like
what and we make people who are doing
badly still do well and that actually
kind of down regulates the evolutionary
pressure in the whole system like why
would we want to do that and of course
over here we can have a kind of left
perspective that says yeah but some
people are getting ahead using shared
services that the government pays for
from everybody's tax money that they
aren't actually really accounting for
and they're affecting the Commons
negatively in a way that is
externalizing the cost everyone else so
that they're being claimed to be more
entrepreneurial it just means they're
extracting from the Commons and
externalizing cost of the Commons better
and do we do we really want to let
people die on the footsteps of hospitals
because they don't have money or
insurance you know in the fully
individualistic libertarian kind of idea
and fully libertarian kind of ideology
can't solve multipolar traps
and so like but there's there's clearly
truth in both of these and they are
clearly neither complex enough to
actually handle reality in which there
are bottom-up effects or the individuals
effect the whole and there's also
top-down effects for the wholes in turn
affect the individual and there's
feedback and feed forward loops and
neither of them are factoring those
enough but the debate process doesn't
bring about dialectic right the debate
processes here actually make the idea
more polarized to get people on this
side emphasize rhetoric over real
sense-making and emphasize winning over
collectively trying to make sense
together so the debate process is not a
good sense making process it's a
narrative warfare process dialectic is
different where it says okay I think we
have some truth and not all of it I
think you have some let's endeavour
together earnestly to figure out the
things that we're all interested in
figuring out and then we start to say
okay well do we want that do we want
better individuals who are more
sovereign independent of environment dot
nobody doesn't want that or do we want
holes that support all the individuals
within them to do better well done we
want that too but the way that we've
done social services makes oftentimes
some of them makes the people not more
sovereign but more dependent so it's
actually not making better people it's
making more comfortable but shittier
people right and the way that we incent
individuals over here in sense people
who are entrepreneurial but by
externalizing costs to the Commons and
creating radical wealth inequality so
it's not incentivizing the most truly
creative and intelligent and good people
it's incentivizing effective sociopathy
and things like that so like neither of
these are doing all that good at the
thing they're even claiming to do so how
do we create social services Collective
processes that condition healthier
people who are more sovereign how do we
create environments that condition
people who do better in any environment
right that actually conditions strength
and resilience and sovereignty in the
individuals who then in turn affect the
environments in ways that support the
increased sovereignty of everybody else
that's a totally higher-order way of
starting to think about the relationship
between them that starts to recognize
the
inexorable failing on both of those
perspectives and and that what the
approach would take is more complex
right that's an example of starting to
move towards synthesis from a thesis and
an antithesis right and if you if you
look at even personal things in your
life you're wrestling with like okay do
I want to accept and love reality and
people and myself as I am or do I want
to like help strive to make things
better there they're similar like those
types of things you'll find a thesis
antithesis everywhere where the actual
insight to synthesis is novel insight
not contained in either of those if I
when I say accept you as you are right
now or help work to change you to make
you better and I see those as as
different it's because I'm seeing you as
a noun and I'm seeing you as a fixed
thing or accept you as you are you are
this current state whereas if I see you
as a process if I see you as a verb I
see you as a becoming that is different
than you were yesterday and different
than you were when you were two right
then accepting you as you are and
includes dynamism includes the impulse
to change grow and evolve so I can
accept you fully as you are which in
love you is you are which includes
accepting and loving the impulse to grow
and expand and include and transcend so
I can support you to become more not on
the basis of judging you as insufficient
but loving you completely including
loving the evolutionary trajectory
inside of the array but that insight of
you as a verb rather than as a noun was
actually not captured in either of these
so the dialectic process of saying like
okay well how do I see the partial truth
here construct this fully and then how
do I see the partial truth here
construct this fully and then what new
insights bring these together in the
higher order perspective that is more
complex and more nuanced than either of
them so that's kind of a dialectic
process and it might not just be to
thesis antithesis might be lots of
perspectives this is it - why would this
is a process that I would love to see
people start
to sing out for sense-making of whenever
they're talking with someone start by
seeking to understand before seeking to
be understood and seek for the truth
value and what people are saying not
just the wrongness but then don't
holistically throw out what they're
saying as totally wrong or totally true
be able to separate that there is signal
and noise and then be able to say if I
see signal from a number of sources how
does that fit together into higher order
perspective this this is another sense
making process you mentioned emotion and
vulnerability as key components of sense
making could you that may seem a little
bit counterintuitive to people can you
explain what you mean by that
if I want to make sense of the world
well and I'm gonna engage in some
communication processes with other
people to make sense of the world with
some collective sense making then I want
them to share true information with me
to not dis inform nor withhold so how do
I create the trust and psychological
safety for them to do that well I'm
probably gonna have to do that too and
so how do we create mutual trust and
psychologic safety that we're not going
to use the information that we're
sharing with each other and game
theoretic ways with each other that's a
huge part and if people don't have some
spaces and some relationships where they
feel like they can actually share fully
openly honestly and feel trust in that
their sense making is gonna be radically
curtailed right to what they can just do
on their own and without anybody's
ability to help error correct them with
full sharing also one of the sources of
bias is identifying with what I believe
because it because I'm identifying with
part of an in-group that believes that
thing or because I am special or smart
or right or whatever for believing that
thing so the the impulse to be right
means that I won't seek to understand
other perspectives and so if I'm gonna
actually seek to understand the truth
value in other perspectives like
earnestly try and get what they are
seeing what where they're coming from I
have to stop seeing it the way that I'm
seeing it for a little while and I also
have to completely suspend debate and
narrative warfare and the impulse to be
right and all of that and so there is a
deeper human connection that's involved
there's also something there's a
psychological process that almost seems
like a spiritual process where for me to
really try and get where you're coming
from on a topic I have to really take
your perspective well what is it in me
that is taking your perspective because
it's not my perspective right it it is
actually having to drop the way that I
see things to really try and see it the
way that you see things to make sense of
it so that means that it is some come
there's a capacity in me that can
witness my perspective that can also
witness your perspective but it is
deeper than the current perspective I
have and we all know we can change our
beliefs and there's still something that
is us so there is a us Ness that is
deeper than the belief system to be able
to really try to make sense of someone
else I actually have to move into that
level of self that is deeper than belief
systems
what do you hope that people will get
from it I would like if they are looking
at their own biases and saying okay
where do I have emotional needs that are
affecting what I believe where do I have
in-group out-group stuff happening where
am I actually doing disinformation where
you know like all what are my cognitive
biases well how do I even know well let
me go look up the list of cognitive
biases and start to inventory them keeps
talking about epistemology like and what
the axioms are I don't even know what
the fuck that means how do I actually go
explore what the right steps of logical
process an axiom are can i empower my
own learning so if people felt inspired
to learn how to learn better and then
inspired to create relationships with
other people where they actually do care
about understanding what is true and
real so that they can also have a better
relationship with what is meaningful and
being able to make choices line to that
and where they're endeavoring to
understand what is true and real
together and also endeavoring to create
an intact information ecology where no
one is dis informing anybody which is as
much or even more an emotional process
as it is a cognitive one because to
really create an intact information
ecology involves vulnerability and
intimacy that's what happens getting out
of a game theoretic context where I say
oh our well-beings are shared well what
if you defect on me I have to actually
create a situation and Trust to be able
to share real information so then I get
to see where my own wounds make it make
me incapable of trusting or of or
revealing her so I'd be I mean those
would be things that I would be happy if
people looked at the emotional and
cognitive and overwhelmed by time and
lazy and biased and whatever sources of
where they aren't sense-making well and
endeavored to work on those and I'd be
happy if if maybe you guys with revell
wisdom took a lot of people who you
interview who like maybe one thing they
have in common is they're all people who
are endeavoring to make sense well and
started to ask them more about
sense-making processes that they employ
so people can actually learn like Brett
could talk about here's how evolutionary
theory here's things that we know from
evolution is here here's how you can
apply this as an epistemic tool or Eric
could talk about here our principles in
the philosophy of science and in physics
that are valuable tools in understanding
reality those types of things and then
if they were even not that many people
who started to really think about break
downs and information ecology better and
write on that more and those ideas were
able to start to become better
understood and be happy about that well
if we look at the framework of sharing
things that are truthful true and
representative we start with the
truthful side we would need to remove
the incentive for disinformation and the
first major source there is kind of
market it's the game theoretic dynamics
that emerge from market type dynamics
and so again if I have two different
branches of the government competing for
budget or different representatives who
are supposedly both seeking to be in
benefit of the country competing for
percentage of the budget now they have
the incentive to dis inform whoever's
allocating the budget dis inform the
public dissin form each other which
means that the total level of
coordination just sucks right and this
happens this is corporate politics
inside of corporations this happens
everywhere so as long as we have
separate balance sheets right as long as
the different intelligence agencies are
competing for that as long as as people
we have several balance sheets then we
have a fundamental basis that my
well-being is separable from and
oftentimes directly rivalries with yours
and with others and with the Commons so
then we will compete with each other for
a lot of things
and we will engage in in at the worst
case physical warfare kinetic warfare
but will mostly engage in economic
warfare competing against each other and
at the cost of the Commons and
information and narrative warfare also
at the cost of the information Commons
and each other so to really get over
that we would need to couple or we need
to create alignment between agencies
right between what you have intention to
do and what is also in my well-being and
vice versa which means that we would
need to have more coupling between our
well-beings which means we would need to
have a different process of resource
provisioning and I will say that the the
type of system that could do that
adequately has never been proposed in
any kind of major way because obviously
none of the systems ever proposed so far
or tried do that but if we have a rival
risk relationship with each other
information will be part of that rivalry
and will damage the information ecology
in the same way we damage the physical
environment or or each other
kinetically so that's a big ask
right so our balance sheets are kind of
at the foundation of what create
rivalries dynamics and this is at the
level of corporations at the level of
individuals where it grounds above the
families of the level of nations so can
we still have private nation states that
could benefit each other at the expense
of others or Commons that share
information perfectly so like if we
really want to say how do we have a
perfectly intact global information
ecology it couldn't happen within the
context of nation states and private
balance sheets and political left's and
rights and in-group out-group type
structures it would take us a while to
talk about what something post game
theoretic might look like but if you
want to just start to intuit it you say
well if we look at all of the neurons in
your brain or all of the cells in your
body
they're all their own agents right like
the cell self-organizes and I can take
it out of you and put in a be
traditional keep self-organizing for
period controlled by its own internal
genetic code but even it's your body
something like 70 trillion individual
cells those cells are organizing in a
way that's best for them as individuals
and best for the ones around them and
best for the whole simultaneously than
either sacrificing themselves for the
whole nor they sacrificing others for a
game theoretic benefit and this is true
at the level of cell to cell interaction
but it's also a trickle of organ to
organ interaction or organ system to
organ system or cell to organ right like
it fractally in all these levels
vertical and horizontal there is a kind
of symbiotic process that happens and if
you tried to model like the organs and a
capitalist relationship with each other
where they were trying to the heart and
the lungs were competing against each
other for scarce resource to hoard as
much resource for feature as possible
and you model that out and happening at
the cellular level buddy dies very
quickly cancer cells are actually doing
that right a cancer cell is doing what
is good for it in the near term but bad
for the whole and it will end up killing
the whole and killing itself in the
process and but the cancer cell only
happened because the body as a whole had
some Mis health that had carcinogenesis
exceed the immune response capacity to
deal with the carcinogenesis so the
whole was already sick to make the
individual sick to some degree right
there's a feedback and feed-forward
process between the parts and the whole
if you think about like vision and the
way that parallax error correction and
parallax occurs in vision one eye
doesn't give me peripheral vision and it
doesn't give me depth perception two
eyes together give me something that and
also the single I will have errors that
aren't corrected for the two eyes
together the overlap of what they both
see but also the difference of what one
sees and the other one doesn't allows
any error in this eye to be corrected
for
Aaron this I and it allows peripheral
vision and depth perception so this is a
place where not only are the eyes not in
competition for which one is seen as
true but the process of how they're
related in the optical cortex gives me
error correction on the on the
imperfections in each of them and it
gives me new synergistic information
that neither of them had on their own
that's fucking amazing to think about
right and this is true like your brain
is a whole processes information that no
individual of the types that no
individual neuron or sub neural networks
are processing and individual neurons
can get something wrong but there's
error correcting processes that don't
propagate that but but the processes do
propagate the true information so we're
like well how the fuck does it work that
we get that the information processing
that each of the parts are doing goes
through a communication protocol that
error corrects the false parts and also
gives parallax on the true parts where
we get not only the truth of all the
parts but a way of binding that together
for synergistically higher-order
information the cells our sense making
and they're communicating they're
signaling with each other right a
hormone is a communication a
neurotransmitter like those are all
signaling processes but they don't have
a game theoretic relationship with each
other right they actually have a
mutually symbiotic relationship with
each other so they are supporting each
other sense making in that way they're
the lungs obviously do better if the
heart's doing better as opposed to doing
worse if they the heart is doing better
so if we just start to kind of imagine
into what type of communication
processes protocols would have to happen
between humans that allowed for error
correction on any individuals
perceptions but allowed the true parts
of everyone's perceptions to be
separated from the air parts and then
all the true parts to be synthesized at
a higher order of complexity than
individuals could do on their own when
we think about the civilization of the
future and the collective intelligence
of the future we think about that one
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
cause to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon